Look at this! here I put in my hand between
this lamp and the wall. On the wall we can
see the shadow of my hand, you can also see
that the shadow is magnified compared to the
real size of my hand. This is a magnification
and this is the most fundamental microscope
that you can make right! If you put in lenses
and things that just makes it more of a compact
device but the principles is sort of like
this. Notice that no light passes through
my hand, we only se the shadow, one can say
that my hand fully absorbed light, and in
bright field microscopy that is the feature
you are looking for, absorption of light into
the sample and the more light it absorbs the
darker spots you get on the viewing screen.
Alright, now you probably know the most basic
things about light microscopy, welcome to
the first lecture in this materials characterization
course, in which we will talk about light
microscopy. It's good to get a good understanding
in light microscopy because it will help you
out in the further chapters of the course,
especially when we talk about electron microscopy
and especially transmission electron microscopy,
because most techniques in those are directly
comparable to light microscopy.
Welcome to the first lecture in light microscopy,
if you haven't checked the demonstration movie
on a light microscope I suggest you do that,
before you start viewing this lecture. The
sample preparation movies you can chose to
view afterwards if you like. The course book
starts with a section on geometrical optics,
I will leave that as an home exercise for
you to catch up on because I will not talk
about that in this lecture. What I do want
to talk about is dark-field and bright-field
imaging and if you take some fundamentals
about light interactions with the sample,
either it can be reflected, or absorbed in
the sample, or it can have a phase effect
on the wavelength of the light that passes
through. This is the two things that can happen
when light is lit upon the sample.
I will show you a detailed sketch about this,
first I draw a reference wave and that ray
passes through nothing so it has no effect
on anything, it just passing through. Then
I draw a second ray of light here that will
go through a sample that absorbs part of it,
when it goes through here part of it will
be absorbed and the amplitude of the wave
will therefore be smaller. The third ray,
I draw here, will pass through an object that
has a phase-effect on the wave, and that means
it will retard the wave and the phase of it,
so it will not come into sync with the other
waves. This can be for example a material
were you have different refractive indexes,
then you have effects like this. What you
can see here in these examples is that if
you have a bright field image in the microscope,
what you are looking for, the contrast in
the picture, will be depending completely
on absorption and that means that if your
sample is not absorbing so much compared to
the surroundings, then the image will be very
weak in contrast and it will be very hard
to see any details in it.
That's why you start using these phase techniques.
It's for example phase-contrast and differential
interference contrast, I will talk on that
in detail in the second lecture. At the moment
I think it's important to know that either
you have absorption or phase effects on the
waves.
In bright field imaging of the microscope,
what you do is that you collect all the transmitted
light that passes through the sample and all
the light that is not absorbed or reflected
in the sample. That gives you this classic
microscope image that you perhaps seen before
from undergraduate school. This technique
is good if the sample has high absorption
in its features, because then you will have
good contrast. The reverse side of this technique
is the dark-field imaging, in this technique
what you do then is instead of looking at
all transmitted, unaffected light, you cancel
out that light and only look at the light
that is reflected (scattered) in the sample. That gives
you an image that looks inverse to the bright
field image. All the white parts will become
black in this case and the sample will appear
as it glows by itself when you look upon it.
The dark field image is also an advantage
when you have reflected light from the surface,
you know that light microscopes, you saw that
in the demo movie, we can booth have transmitted
light that goes through or you can have reflected
light from top as well. If you only use the
top reflected technique is very handy if you
look for example at metallic samples that
you have etched. In that case all the grains
will have chamfered edges due to the etching
and that will reflect light differently and
if you use dark field imaging on that you
will see the grains very clearly, a good technique
for that.
If I'm going to draw how this basically works,
then it is like this, there is a picture in
the book of this also and I think it's good.
I draw a side view of the microscope here,
and at the bottom I draw the condenser lens
with its aperture. Beneath I draw a top view
so you can see exactly how the aperture of
the condenser looks like. The aperture is
a round disc and in bright field imaging what
you keep is a hole that looks like this that
you can change the size of, that's the aperture
size. The aperture cancels out everything
that's outside the hole, light can only pass
through it. That is for bright field imaging.
In the middle I put in a glass slide with
the sample, and on top of that you have the
objective under the microscope that picks
up the light. What you can see here is that
when the light comes through the condenser
it will match up so all the light will be
transmitted through the sample and then will
be picked up by the matching objective here,
that gives you this transmitted bright field
image. Instead if you have, I draw that on
the other side, here to the right, the dark
field imaging case. What you do then is instead
of having this hole of the condenser aperture
you have a round disc in the center. You cancel
out all the light that's in the center, what
that means is that the light you shine upon
the sample will come in at a specific angle
into it. If the light is not affected by the
sample it will go out in the same direction.
The smart thing here in dark field imaging
is that if you have objective at top that
is built so that it matches this angle, and
if the light is unaffected and passes out
at same angle it will miss the objective and
will not be picked up. If that's the case
you will only see a black screen in the microscope
when viewing. Because all light has been canceled
out and goes outside of the objective. But
if the light is interacting in the sample
and changes angle, if it's refracted in the
sample then it will take a different angle
out from the sample and then some of it will
come into the objective and that means when
you look at the image it will actually look
like the sample itself is bright. Then you
get this reverse effect of bright field image.
The next thing you need to have a understanding
about is phase-plates. Phase plates were sort
of discovered by accident, I think it was
by Rayleigh, he poured out some acid on top
of glass slide and then he found out that
this etched down the glass very little, half
a wavelength of the light and that had this
kind of phase effect when he did some optical
investigation of it. A phase plate is this
glass slide that you
have etched an annulus ring on top of.
The smart thing with this,
that is if you take this phase plate glass
slide with this specific ring shaped structure
and then you create an equal aperture in the
condenser with the same annulus shape, this
is a development step from the dark-field
central stop aperture, here we have a specific
spacing around not just a central stopper.
If you do that then all the light that goes
through the sample and is unaffected will
have the same angle as in the dark-field imaging
mode, but you pick up that light with the
objective, you created a different objective
that can pick up that light as well. Then
that light, if you put this phase-plate on
top of the objective, that unaffected light
will go through this etched ring of this glass
slide, that we call the phase-plate. That
means that the wavelength will be shifted
half a wavelength compared to if it were refracted
in the sample. If the sample has a different
refractive index, then the angle out from
the sample by the light beam will be different
and that means that light when it hit the
phase-plale will not go through this etched
ring, only unaffected light that goes through
it, all other light will go somewhere else
on the phase-plate. That means that you will
have two waves that goes out on top of the
phase plate that will be retarded half a wavelength
from each other. What is the conclusion of
this, light that is interacting with the sample
will be shifted half a wavelength compared
to non-affected light, these two light rays
will interfere with each other and create
destructive interference and that gives you
this thing called phase contrast. Because
it is destructive interference you will have
a contrast feature were things will look bright
and dark depending on the refractive index
of the sample, so this gives the possibility
to view samples that has the same absorption
of light but different refractive indexes.
Typical examples is if you look at biological
objects a cell for example, living cells,
that has liquids and things inside it that
is transparent compared to the glass and the
water that you have perhaps have put around
it on the objective glass. If you put this
in under phase contrast technique then you
can see if there are different refractive
indexes of the cell and the surrounding water
and this will create contrast and you will
more easily see it compared to if you just
use bright field imaging. That is the natural
development step up from dark-field imaging.
That's phase contrast technique.
This is enough for lecture one, now I talked
about bright field imaging, dark-field imaging,
and a little bit about phase-contrast and
the phase plate. What I want You to do now
is to solve some of the problems as suggested
below and then you continue on lecture two.
In lecture two I will talk about differential
interference contrast and polarization techniques.
Alright, see you on lecture two.